A Finding Aid to the Esta Nesbitt Papers, circa 1942-1981, in the Archives of American Art AAA.nesbesta
Archives of American Art
Esta Nesbitt papers
bulk 1964-1975
circa 1942-1981
AAA.nesbesta
Archives of American Art
10.4 Linear feet
The papers of illustrator, xerography artist, filmmaker, and educator Esta Nesbitt measure 10.4 linear feet and date from circa 1942-1981. Found within the papers are biographical material, correspondence, writings, xerography research files, project and exhibition files, and printed material. Much of the collection relates to Nesbitt’s xerography art work. Additionally, the collection includes motion picture film and sound recordings related to her film and performance work.
Nesbitt, Esta
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Esta Nesbitt papers were donated by Saul Nesbitt, her husband, to the Archives of American Art in 1981.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into 6 series:
Biographical Materials, 1964-circa 1981 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1, 11)
Correspondence, 1942, 1964-1976 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1, OV 14)
Writings, 1959-circa 1973 (1.3 linear feet; Box 1-2, 12, OV 15)
Xerography Research Files, circa 1966-1974 (2.5 linear feet; Box 2-4, 11, OV 16)
Project and Exhibition Files, circa 1966-1981 (5.1 linear feet, Box 4-8, 11, 13, OV 17-19)
Printed Material, 1942-circa 1944, circa 1963-1977 (0.9 linear feet; Box 9-10, OV 20)
Related Archival Materials note
The Esta Nesbitt papers at Center for Creative Photography at University of Arizona contain 3 linear feet related to her xerography artwork and exhibitions, dated 1966-1983.
Papers related to Nesbitt’s fashion illustrations are found at the Kellen Design Archives at The New School in New York City. T
he Esta Nesbitt papers at the University of Minnesota Libraries Children’s Literature Research Collections are related to Nesbitt’s children’s book illustrations, dated 1964-1969.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of illustrator, xerography artist, filmmaker, and educator Esta Nesbitt measure 10.4 linear feet and date from circa 1942-1981. Found within the papers are biographical material, correspondence, writings, xerography research files, project and exhibition files, and printed material. Much of the collection relates to Nesbitt’s xerography art work. Additionally, the collection includes motion picture film and sound recordings related to her film and performance work.
Nesbitt’s primary collaborators, correspondents, and subjects of investigation are not concentrated in any one series but rather recur throughout the collection. Nesbitt worked closely with Anibal Ambert, Merle English at Xerox Corporation, and the Whitney Museum of American Art. She read and wrote about the accrual of information, Albert Einstein, Asian religion and philosophy, communication, computer technology, documentation practices, energy, psychology, Samuel Beckett, and states of consciousness. Chinese characters and an image of Allen Ginsberg appear repeatedly in Nesbitt’s works. Subjects of study and experimentation include 3M and Kodak technologies, color, film, morphology, participatory and performance art, shadows, sound, street works, xerography, and Xerox machines.
Biographical material revolves mostly around Nesbitt’s work as a professor at Parsons School of Design. Records include Nesbitt’s resumé, an exhibition history, motion picture film of the inside of her studio, and teaching files.
Correspondence contains personal letters from family members, and professional correspondence with fellow artists and employees of Xerox Corporation. Much of the series is correspondence between Nesbitt and fellow artists Alan Leder, David Lyle, and R.E. Wood, and is philosophical in nature. Correspondence with Xerox Corporation documents her relationship with the corporation between 1970 and 1972, when they underwrote her experiments in xerography.
Writings include illustrated journals, journals, notebooks, loose notes, and transcripts. The content of the writings varies widely throughout the series and includes artwork, sketches, diagrams, annotated clippings, transcripts of conversations, Nesbitt’s writings about her dreams and family, details about her daily life, and notes about artists’ materials, film, and sound.
Xerography Research Files document Nesbitt’s experiments with xerography, which she often refers to in her papers as “Xerox Xplore.” Contents include Nesbitt’s definitions of xerography terms; Xerox equipment brochures; clippings; xerography studies; notebooks about Nesbitt’s plans, work with color, and xerography study details; and slides and transparencies of completed xerography prints.
Project and Exhibition Files consist of a variety of documentation related to Nesbitt’s books, exhibitions, films, performance and participatory art, and other projects. This series contains the bulk of the collection’s motion picture films and sound recordings. The film and sound performance piece titled “Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On,” the piece Walk Up – Tape On, the film “Light Times 499,” and exhibitions of Nesbitt’s xerography work and her series of work called Shadow Paintings are the most prominent subjects of the series.
Printed Material includes books, clippings, magazines, exhibition announcements, catalogs, and press releases about Nesbitt’s interests, artwork, exhibitions, and galleries that exhibited her work. Some of the material is annotated.
Biographical/Historical note
Esta Nesbitt (1918-1975) was an illustrator, xerography artist, filmmaker, and educator who lived and worked in New York City. She was a fashion illustrator for about two decades before becoming a children’s book illustrator, performance artist, xerography artist, and filmmaker.
Nesbitt taught at Parsons School of Design from 1964 to 1974. Around 1970, Nesbitt created the piece Walk Up – Tape On with her Parsons students. The piece involved documenting social interaction by taping themselves to each other and then others as they walked through New York City, creating what Nesbitt called a "living organism," before presenting themselves to the Whitney Museum of American Art. The event was documented with film, photography, and audio recordings.
In 1970, Nesbitt contacted Xerox Corporation about creating experimental art investigations of the Walk Up – Tape On documentation using Xerox machines in their New York City office. During Nesbitt’s time at Xerox, she experimented with many different copying machines, materials, and techniques to create what came to be known as xerographic artworks. She invented three xerography techniques: transcapsa, photo-transcapsa, and chromacapsa. A transcapsa work is created by moving a piece of material over the copier's window during the printing cycle. A photo-transcapsa work is created by moving a photographic image over the copier's window during the printing cycle. Chromacapsa is a process of adding color to xerographic works using Xerox copiers. Nesbitt referred to her work at Xerox as "Xerox Xplore," which culminated with the exhibition “Xerography - Extensions in Art” (1971-1972) and the commission of the print All the Lines are Nines.
To demonstrate “the media bombardment surrounding ‘everyman’ today,” Nesbitt created a film and sound performance piece titled “Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On” in 1969. The performance consisted of five Super 8 film projectors and a multi-layered soundtrack. Nesbitt further experimented with filmmaking and xerography with the films “Folding/Struck” and “Light Times 499,” which was created with Anibal Ambert. Her interest in xerography is further illustrated in the exhibition “Electrostatic Structures: ‘New Morphs’” (1972-1973). The exhibition “1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment” was a culmination of her interest in participatory art.
Nesbitt died November 30, 1975 in New York City. Three posthumous exhibitions include “Esta Nesbitt: Xerography Prints” (1976) at The Art Center of Waco, “Memorial Exhibition of Drawing and Illustrations by Esta Nesbitt” (1977) at Parsons School of Design, and “Electroworks” (1979-1981) at the George Eastman House.
Ambert, Anibal; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955 -- Portraits. ##naf; English, Merle; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-; Leder, Alan J.; Lyle, David; Parsons School of Design--Faculty; Whitney Museum of American Art; Wood, R. F.; Xerox Corporation.; Art teachers; Copy art; Diaries; Everyman (motion picture); Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Sketches; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Women artists; Xerography
- Biographical Materials, 1964-circa 1981; Series 1; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, 11
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include Nesbitt’s resume, correspondence, photographic and printed material, and motion picture film. Most of the material revolves around Parsons School of Design, where Nesbitt taught. Correspondence regarding the National Student Strike and Anti-War Exhibit, created to illustrate the students’ opposition to the Vietnam War, includes correspondence between Parsons School of Design and President Richard Nixon. Nesbitt’s studio is documented in this series on two reels of Super 8 film.
  - Resume and Exhibition History, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Film of Nesbitt’s Studio, 1969; 2 Film reels Super 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Nesbitt, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Framemaker’s Award from Silvermine Guild, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pratt Graphic Art Center, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Files, Parsons School of Design (Box 1)
    - Contact Sheets of Nesbitt Teaching, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Contact Sheets of Students, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 1.
    - Correspondence regarding the National Student Strike and Anti-War Exhibit, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - List of Faculty Show Participants, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Photographic Material of a Birthday Party, 1972 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Photographic Material of an Anti-War Exhibit, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Printed Material Regarding the Vietnam War, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Original Labels on Archival Boxes, circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Contact Sheets of Students, circa 1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 7.
  - Oversized Photographic Material of Anti-War Exhibit, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 11.
- Correspondence, 1942; 1964-1976; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 14
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is primarily arranged by the name of correspondent and then chronologically within each folder. Writings, letters, and annotated clippings which were not attached to a letter are arranged chronologically within the respective folder.
  Additional correspondence can be found intermixed with other documents in the Writings, Xerography Research Files, and Projects and Exhibitions series.
  Correspondence includes letters and memos between personal friends and professional colleagues and Nesbitt. Many letters and memos include attachments, such as artwork, annotated clippings, and letters. Letters written by Nesbitt are drafts.
  Correspondents in the Personal and Professional folder include Nesbitt, Edmund Carpenter, Seymour Lipton, Mara Nesbitt, Perry Nesbitt, Saul Nesbitt, Carla and Thom Perry, The Art Center of Waco, National Collection of Fine Arts (Smithsonian), University of California Berkeley, and Westbroadway Gallery. Topics of discussion include life updates, Chinese philosophy, xerography, Nesbitt’s projects (“Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On,” “Light Times 499,” Walk up-Tape on, "Xerox Xplore") and exhibitions (“Esta Nesbitt: Xerography Prints,” “Magic Machines”).
  Correspondence between Nesbitt, Alan Leder, David Lyle, and R.E. Wood covers a wide range of topics, including Lyle, William Carlos Williams, T.S. Eliot, Mike Weaver, Allen Ginsberg, Paterson NJ, energy and nature, mathematics, and data. Correspondence with Lyle also includes the subjects of Xerox Corporation, xerography, exhibition “Xerography: Extensions in Art,” 3M Co, and mandala. Much of the writing is philosophical in nature and includes annotated letters, articles, and clippings.
  Xerox Corporation correspondence covers Nesbitt’s relationship with and work at Xerox, additional funding possibilities with New School for Social Research, and a New York Times review. Nesbitt’s primary contact at Xerox was Merle English.
  - Personal and Professional, 1942; 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in OV 14.
  - Alan Leder, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - David Lyle, circa 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - David Lyle, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Holt, Rinehart and Winston Regarding Children’s Books, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Michael Phillips Regarding the Most Creative Extraordinary People List, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - R.E. Wood, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Xerox Corporation, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Oversized Personal and Professional Correspondence, 1964-1976; 1942 (Box OV 14)
    Oversized material from Box 1 Folder 14.
  - Oversized Alan Leder Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box OV 14)
    Oversized material from Box 1 Folder 15.
  - Oversized David Lyle Correspondence, circa 1969-1971 (Box OV 14)
    Oversized material from Box 1 Folder 16.
- Writings, 1959-circa 1973; Series 3; 1.3 Linear feet Box 1-2, 12, OV 15
  Additional writings can be found in the Correspondence, Xerography Research Files, and Projects and Exhibitions series.
  Writings are in the form of bound and unbound journals, notebooks, and loose notes. Illustrations, clippings, articles, journal entries, and poetry are interspersed throughout the series, with personal and professional content mixed together. Titles listed below were derived from Nesbitt's handwritten titles on the journal covers.
  Illustrated Journals contain artwork, sketches, diagrams, annotated clippings, and written entries. Subjects are mainly painting techniques, materials, and ideas. Other subjects touched on include Chinese characters, calligraphy, shadow paintings, the future of art, energy, morphs, memory, and meaning. The transformation of art using different techniques and materials is also a common theme. Projects discussed include the 1972-1973 projects Balls, Flower, and Big Foot.
  Many of these subjects are also subjects of Nesbitt's journals, which also include entries of a personal nature dealing with dreams, Nesbitt's family, life, death, and reality. Other subjects include Chinese characters and scrolls, and Samuel Beckett’s characters Molloy and Malone. Also, notes related to phone calls, appointments, travel, project tasks, teaching, family life, and funding concerns are found in her journals.
  Notebooks contain notes and clippings related to artists’ materials, religion, Chinese philosophy and civilization, changes in consciousness, psychology, film techniques, transmission of sound, and documentation practices. The notebook labeled “Film and Slide Techniques and Ideas” also contains ideas, lists, diagrams, and test notes. Projects “Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On,” burnt Xeroxes, and stair patterns are also mentioned.
  Transcripts include notes and conversations transcribed from tapes. Topics include xerography, project "Xerox Xplore," exhibition “Xerography: Extensions in Art,” and copyrights and permissions for publication. The original recordings from which the transcripts were made are not part of the collection.
  - Illustrated Journal, 1964-1966; "Painting Notes 1965/66" (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 2.
  - Illustrated Journal, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 1.
    Separated Materials note
    Transcribed from journal cover: "Notes & Refs. 1965/66/some 67"
  - Illustrated Journal, 1972; "Notes & Drawings of new work & names etc / about Morphs / Sept -72" (Box 1, Folder 24-27)
    Oversized material for Folders 25 and 26 housed in OV 15.
  - Illustrated Journal, 1973; "'BALLS' & Crushed/Foldings -Feb 17.73 / ADD April 19.73 a 'new kind of chart' / 'Flower' / January 14.1973 / Feb 14.73 'BIG FOOT'" (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Illustrated Journal, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Oversized material housed in OV 15.
  - Journal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Journal, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Journal, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Journal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Journal, 1970; "June 19/1970 'Correspondence Notes'" (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Journal, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Journal, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Journal, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - Journal, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Journal, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notebooks (Box 1)
    - Class Notes, “Materials of the Artist”, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Reading Notes, 1967-1968; 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Film and Slide Techniques and Ideas, 1969; "INTERMEDIA Spring 1969 / 'Parsons Movie'" (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Documentation Practices, 1969-1970; "Scientific Notebook I - began Sept 22/69" (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      Oversized material for Folder 3 housed in OV 15.
  - Notes about the Transmission of Sound and Data, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notes about Women Artists’ Exhibits and Organizations, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes for Proposals, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poetry and Word-Mandala, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transcripts (Box 2)
    - Notes and Conversations, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Conversations, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Illustrated Journal, 1964-1966 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 22.
  - Oversized Illustrated Journal, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 23.
  - Oversized Illustrated Journal, 1972 (Box OV 15)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folders 25 and 26.
  - Oversized Illustrated Journal, circa 1973 (Box OV 15)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 29.
  - Oversized Notebook on Documentation Practices, 1969-1970 (Box OV 15)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 3.
- Xerography Research Files, circa 1966-1974; Series 4; 2.5 Linear feet Box 2-4, 11, OV 16
  Xerography Research Files are arranged by predominant format: printed material, notebooks and notes, and xerography studies. However, due to the nature of the material, all formats are mixed throughout the series. The Xerox brochures and notebooks are arranged alphabetically, and the folders containing loose notes and the xerography studies are arranged chronologically.
  Notebooks labeled Xerox Xplore 1-3 are arranged in multiple folders to accommodate a large number of enclosures and for preservation purposes. The loose contents of Xerox Xplore 1 were previously moved to a separate folder and their original order is unknown. For Xerox Xplore 2, the original location of the enclosures is noted on inserts. Xerox Xplore 3 was disassembled and enclosures were kept in their original location.
  Xerography materials also can be found in the Projects and Exhibitions series. Documents with related topics can also be found in the Correspondence, Writings, Projects and Exhibitions, and Printed Material series.
  Xerography Research Files include brochures, clippings, notebooks, loose notes, photographic slides and transparencies, and xerography studies. "Xerox Xplore," what Nesbitt called her experiments with xerography, is the prominent subject of the series. However, the series also contains references to many other projects, people, equipment, materials, and techniques. Annotations exist throughout the series.
  Brochures are for specific Xerox machine models, referred to throughout the series, and paper types. Clippings concern color, equipment, tools, and techniques related to film, photography, xerography, computer art, computerized communications, computer and video animation, copyrights, and patents.
  Notebooks contain lists, ideas, plans, diagrams, sketches, artwork, handwritten tape and conversation transcripts, phone messages, inventories, printed materials, reading notes, and correspondence.TTitles listed below were derived from Nesbitt's handwritten titles appearing on the the covers. Notes mainly concern xerography materials, equipment, techniques, and processes, including the possibilities of working with color. Her work with color is most prevalent in the notebooks labeled: “Xerox Think-Bank Color,” “Xerox Xplore 3 Chromacapsagraphics,” and “Xerox Xplore Chroma-Capsagraphy.” In addition to bound notebooks, there are two folders with loose notes, and some of the notebooks were unbound for preservation purposes. Xerography studies contain photocopied images as well as source images and materials for Nesbitt’s xerography experiments. Notes regarding materials, equipment, techniques, processes, and dates of creation are located on the back of images and loose notes between images. Inventory charts, located in the notebook labeled “Xerox Xplore 2,” document many of the prints created for the xerography experiments with a short description of specific studies, date of creation, size, equipment, and technique used.
  - Typescript of Xerography Terms, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Brochure and Article on Paper Types, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Xerox Brochures (Box 2)
    - Automatic Document Feeder 2400 and 3600, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Computer Forms Printer, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Continuous Printer, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Convenience Copier 4000, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Copier, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Drafting Printer and Practices, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Engineering Print System, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - How the Xpect Company Found Out What It Was, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Microfilm Printer, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Reduction Duplicator, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Telecopier, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Xerox Standard Equipment, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Xerox Systems Centers, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, circa 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Oversized material housed in OV 16.
  - Magazines, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 2.
  - Notebooks (Box 2)
    - Notebook, 1970 May-July; "May 27/70 to July 5/70 SOME XEROX CORP. NOTES IN HERE" (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
    - Xerox "Holding-Patterns", 1970 December-1971 January; "Xerox Book Dec 8/70 / 'XEROX' / 'HOLDING-PATTERNS'" (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Xerox Plans and Projections, 1971 January-April; "Jan 8.1971 / XEROX Notebook / Plans & Projections / B&W Book 1" (Box 2, Folder 32-34)
    - Xerox Plans and Projections, 1971 June-October; "June 12.71 / Xerox Notebook / Plans & Projections / Book 2" (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - Xerox Think-Bank Color, 1971 January; "XEROX THINK-BANK / COLOR NOTEBOOK 1" (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Xerox Xplore 1, 1971 January-March; "XEROX 'Xplore' Notebook #1 / January '71 to March 11.1971" (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Xerox Xplore 1 (continued), 1971 January-March (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Xerox Xplore 2, 1971 March-December; "Xerox Xplore Notebook #2 / March 11.71 continuing" (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
    - Xerox Xplore 3 Chromacapsagraphics, 1971 December; "Xerox Xplore / Special Notebook #3 (color transfer) chromacapsagraphics / Dec 15-1971" (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Xerox Xplore Bibliography, 1971 July (Box 3, Folder 10)